[music]
Friends, hello, her podcast is currently
untitled, and Bohdana Neborak and Nastya
Evdokymova met again
in the audio lounge for the 18th time in the 18th
episode, in which we talk about the city of
Valerian Pidmogilny, which we
will read closely and discuss and Bohdana and I
have completely different views
on this text and completely different approaches to
reading. I think that it is also worth saying about this.
now I think about the fact that this is
already the 18th episode And it is certainly impressive,
especially now during the war, I realized
that it is very important to have projects that
show you a certain endurance, it does not
necessarily have to be a podcast, it
can be some very private things,
personal practices, but which allow us
not to feel like such dense flies
in Amber and to understand how time moves
because maybe someday you and I
will return to this podcast in
order to remember what and we were what we were.
Our intonations, for sure they
change, for sure they will be different
later, and
you know it, just like
rereading, here you and I are
actually reading these classical texts of Ukrainian
literature, and
every time they seem to be the same, but in
some way different, because they resonate or not
resonate to other
parts of our soul, other
areas in our brain, and this is also terribly
interesting because it is
very important that
you and the text meet. This is a kind of
rendezvous, and it may not
happen even if the book is very cool.
And I think this is generally very important
in in the practice of reading, that is, it often happens that
there is a cool classic book that everyone
admires. And you pick it up and it
doesn't work for you, maybe you just need a
little time. Probably for me this time,
because of course there is reading for pleasure, there is
reading for work, and for work I
had to I would like to read the city and
form my opinion, but my inner
world opposes the novel the city at this
moment because I cannot help myself
I can't experience this city for myself
because
pre-war Kyiv seems
irrelevant to me. And after the war I didn't live in Kyiv
long enough to rediscover this city for myself,
because I chose a
course for life in a country estate
for myself this summer.
I don't need in order to win something
or discover something with a word. Stepan Radchenko is a
very distant and not very
clear hero for me at this particular moment. Also
, the events of the city take place in
autumn, autumn in particular.
And you will answer them, I
decided that such
rules of the game should be established and you have no chance to
disagree, this is just like a public
interview for which I did not prepare, it
will be a public
interview, but in a completely private
atmosphere of a cozy audio lounge, as
it happens always I'm very sorry
that we have an appointment at 11 and I can't
pour
myself a drink Well, fine, but you see, I'm drinking water from my glass
Well, I have a piece of lime hanging there. It
adds to the flair, let's go, and I have a
soft fluffy cat scratching here, it
also adds to the other flair, coziness, coziness
and warmth.
So, in 1928, a friend published
Valerian Pidmogilny's novel city, which
begins with two epigraphs, two quotes
and a friend of them, I quote how you can be
free,
Eucrite When you have a body Anatol Franz,
i.e. The novel the city begins with a quote by the
French writer of the turn of the 19th-20th
century, Anatole Franz, researchers also
wrote about the fact that in general there are subtypes in the work of
Pidmogilny, as in Franz and so
many similar things between a Frenchman and a
gravedigger, just as between a Frenchman and a
pasan, because we are going according to the rules Roman
My dear friend, I am Anatoliy Franz Roman, Thais
translated Valerian Pidmohylny in general
Valeriy Pidmohylny knew the French well, the
Roman, the French literary
tradition, he also translated Honore de
Balzac and about the sphere of Merimee and many
others and he translated these texts as a
francophone in particular in order to master
this literature the urn tradition of the French
novel that has already happened, which has already
sounded loudly,
and in this novel Thais there is carnal love
there is a Hero who seeks to
convert an
actress Thais He seeks to change her
just as the hero of the novel Valerian
Podmohylnyi's city seeks to change something in
his life in both the texts contain love and
there are many carnal desires, for what purpose did
Valerian Pidmogilny use such an
epigraph and there are three theses I read a scientific
article that describes them to anyone who is interested
I can send it privately, write to me
and ask and such purposes were in this
epigraph the first is advertising, because
Anatoly Frantz's novel was published in 27th
and Pidmohylnyi's novel was published in 28th.
Pidmohylnyi translated Franz and wanted
to tell more people about
his work. The
educational goal was that he imagined an ideal
reader who had the same lecture as
Pidmohylnyi, that is, he read the same texts
sees these connections and illusions can
compare heroes can compare love
in these texts who can dive
deeper into a certain literary context, well
, of course, between cultural communication,
French literature, Ukrainian
literature, Ukrainian literature as a
part of the Great European
literary world, where Ukrainian
literature, what should be included, and
this is what Valerian Pidmogilnyi does.
Valerian
Pidmohylny
Do these traces make Valerian
Pidmohylny a completely European
writer
because, for example, Tais Anatoly Frantz and the
story Yedemo Pasana are in the list of
works that Harold Bloom is such a researcher
who wrote the work Western Canon inscribes
in the European Canon a literary
list of those works that must must
be read And there is And
there is her demo-pasan eating there, should
Valerian Podmohylyny be there, did you think
about this kind question, of course
I will try to answer yes
[music]
unequivocally, French literature is important for Podmohylyny,
which he not only
reads drunkenly, but also covers and leads
to the Ukrainian reader
and clearly
Pidmogylyny is a very ambitious author.
We all know that his debut
book was published when he was 19 years old and he
called it works Volume 1, that is, it sounds
like a
complete collection of future classics. I
think that this is actually a characteristic characteristic of
many authors of that time with different
views, in the end even sometimes from different
generations and literary groups because
they needed to declare themselves and they
felt that they could do it, they
can write in their own language, they can be
published But there is a lot of ego in this,
I would really like to hear a voice
Podmohylnyi I would like to have more
evidence about him, because on the one hand, he is a
key author of the 20th century and some
researchers say that the novel Misto is the
main novel of the 20th century of Ukrainian
literature, on the other hand, he is one of the
most mysterious authors, but should we
get used to the fact that our authors are mysterious
And there is very little left about them here, it's
just important to do this rema right away rk
about age, because we understand that these
19 years of Pidmohylny when he publishes
his debut book are 36 years, which he is
allocated in principle, there are 34 years that he
will spend in freedom, and I am the age at which
Roman misto communicates, which becomes
Pidmohylny's business card, he is
27 years old. He is very young the age for a novelist when
Pidmogilny corresponded with his
close friend Yevgeny Pluzhnik,
they talked about the fact that the fourth
decade is the age when the writer can
begin to fully open up,
we do not know how Pidmogilny will fully open up
, the
phrase about the sandarmoch is already becoming a cliché, but it is true, his
end is also tragic and we know from the
letters that he continued to write there too,
that is, he continued to create like many
imprisoned Ukrainian artists even in the
camps.
his
interrogation protocols and of course I remembered how you and
I talked or Bagryano because
when you read the first interrogation report, you
see one person who sees the world
around him as it is. When you
read each subsequent one, you see a person
who is being tried very hard to break, and
it is terribly bitter. I had such
a very sticky feeling of being watched
from this because they are signed by the
Undertaker's hand, they are very high-quality scans, and it's
like you're standing next to the investigator in this room,
and I also see what they're doing with a
young Ukrainian writer
. We'll never know
if Pidmogilny would have made it into the not-so-
Western Canon of Harold Bloom
at the Faculty of Slavic Studies around
the world because the Soviet Union happened,
but I don't want it to sound
deadly because today
Pidmogilny is coming back, we
're
reading it, foreigners are reading it, he recently
was published in the Czech Republic by a very cool
publishing house and in a good translation and became
popular; a German one was also published which is also
cool, such an avant-garde cover, a
cool translation for me. I want to believe that
Podogylny will slowly return to the
discourse, another matter is that it is very bitter that
when we look at the texts of other authors
of the same years, they are some novels by Hemingway
or Fitzgerald, which simply become
cult
following the paths of which we follow you know My
last trip before the escalation It was a
trip to Spain and there In particular I was
in the city of San Sebastián Really I couldn't help
but think about Hemingway's fiesta about this
simply the most important novel of the lost
generation about this character who
really What character Undertaker has
very little to say to himself about love
about her possibilities and about her place in
this world. Although no matter how hard she tries,
even Pidmohylny has such a certain feeling of
detachment. That is, it is very short and the time, the
texts are actually very different. But if
Pidmohylny
sounded like he could have sounded
if Ukraine was free and independent
state, it is quite possible that you and I
could buy it somewhere in the bookstore,
Shakespeare and Company, a book that
interweaves Hemingway’s novel with Pidmogilny’s
novel, but it is impossible to do this
because Hemingway becomes an
international legend, and unfortunately, unfortunately,
he does not even become a
legend here in Ukraine, in Kyiv, about which
he he writes so much, if we also had an
audio library, we would now pay attention
to our audio shelf, then we would start
pulling out from many different
places, fragment by particle, the various works of
Pydhogilny, his stories, his
translations. We would get his novels,
short stories, and we would teach all this on the
table there would be a lot of different
books, magazines, texts that have not been
reprinted since the 20s, which
remained there in those magazines in that
press of the 20s.
it's just that
they appeared in the 20s and disappeared, they were destroyed
when Podmohylyny was imprisoned, then all this
was removed and it simply disappears from the
discourse or it leaves it is still there in
those magazines and no one has seen it and will not
see it until scientists pull
it out because usually all these magazines
are in such a department in such
departments of libraries when you need to put on a
glove carefully flip through it and
they will give them to everyone and not everyone
will give them but we don’t have enough of this
selection from
[music], a
complete or rather a collection of works with a good
professional literary commentary with
notes and everything else and as far as I
know it may be a secret but bam and
our entire audio room but I am sure that everyone
will keep this secret Vera Pavlovna
gayeva prepares such a text is a
set of texts to be printed. We hope
that it will soon see the light of day and
we will all be able to read it
and work on it, actually. I would like
our conversation to take place on four
thematic levels.
talk and write a lot
really compare let's go pasan and dear
friend and the city of Valerian Pi more
than one dissertation has been written by Podmohylny about this. And what is
even more important, you and I, dear ones, are still
reading and going. It is precisely in
Podmohylny's translation, if you go to any
online and offline bookstore, you will see that
his translation of this text is being republished to
this day, because it remains
relevant The next level is that I can
announce all three levels at once. The
next level is a Ukrainian
urban novel. One more level is the
city as an autobiographical novel and
ultimately the city as a prokiev novel, so I want to
ask you about the first Ukrainian
urban novel, the city, because
urbanism comes with modernism.
Solomiya Pavlychko writes about this in her
discourse on modernism, and Ukrainian
literature is gradually becoming urban
as well, although it will never completely
leave the village,
rural literature, urban literature,
it seems to me that they always exist side by side,
because even a completely urban
resident Mykhailo Kotsyubynskyi goes to the
village goes to Kononivskyi fields for
what to rest from the iron hand of the city and
finally get my intermezzo. Well,
in the 21st century, one of the authors of the podcast,
currently unnamed, Anastasia Evdokymova,
also gets tired of the city and also goes
to the village. In a country estate to rest
from the hand of the city, you see Bohdan. How I
put myself next to Kotsyubynsky skillfully.
You even visited Kryvorivno. Yes, I was there
already the other summer and several summers
ago I spent there and tried to
feel like Ivan the Frank or to lie in a
chair also like Mykhailo Kotsyubynskyi or
to try to sit by the river like
Mykhailo Hrushevskyi, I managed to do all this.
the artist's content
has always been because the city is a theme
for literature, the city is a certain topos, the
city is a certain completely different landscape, the
city is a certain type of consciousness, a
symbol of certain consciousness in the 20s,
Ukrainian poetry also turns to the
city and becomes urban all futurists,
what will they describe about these sounds, the brilliance of the
city's shouts, this is what the poetry of the seed of the
shell is about Saussure writes about the city in
1924. He published a
collection of poems called That's the City, and in
it the mood of loneliness, the mood of
alienation, the mood of the hero who does not
fully accept and perceive this city.
in the
snow, who came with a genius flair and
did it with a stroke of the hand, the
city took all the thoughts,
all the impulses are mine, it’s hidden for me to
moan in his snowy chest, there is a
completely different city in the neoclassicists,
dear audio living room, I hope you
all listened to the tenth episode in which we
they talked in particular about Mykola Zerov and
Bohdan quoted the text Kyiv from the Left
Bank and we know that for Zerov, for
neoclassicists, the city is libraries,
reading rooms, universities, this is some
intellectual space in which they
bathe, which they create in
Ukrainian, this is a city, but this city is not theirs
accepts it because it is a foreign city for them, it is not
Ukrainian culture, it is from Russia, still a
culture
And here is Valerian Pidmohyl he writes his
novel, the city, this novel belongs to the first
Ukrainian urban novels,
intellectual novels. It stands next
to the texts of Vedemontovych Viktor
Petrov, and both authors have a certain
fondness for the problems that
philosophers had to solve in general. That is, it is not an
everyday problem about
today, but something global a person and a city,
I, they are a person and another. And what exactly is
this element of the city? How does Radchenko, the
main character of the novel, the city in this
city feel, because he has two such initiations,
on the one hand, literary, erotic, with
all his personal life, on the other hand,
he is changeable, dual how this city is afraid,
there is something angelic in it, there is something in it, those
children, and maybe not even the city, but the body
of Stepan Radchenko himself and all his
loved ones is the main character.
about the city I really don't like the
format of this podcast, I think we
gave up on the fact that we
arr but for yourself from the very beginning,
because you coquettishly said that you would
ask me a question, but instead you
express a lot of ideas, and then like this,
well, now I will ask you a question, so
I propose to break this system and, after
all, return to the possibility of conducting a
dialogue in which we we are both talking about
the same things from different points of view.
Let's try,
but I will already answer your question
so that you can accept this trauma that
I just caused you unexpectedly
when I changed all the rules
regarding urban literature and urbanism. In
fact,
we have already talked about it dozens of times. times and
in other literatures, this
problem of urban or non-urban
literature does not arise. That is, there is simply a space where
everything happens and this space of action gives
us a stage on which the plot is played out and
certain
ideological issues are resolved. In Ukraine, the situation
is a little different.
the Ukrainian language was forbidden and it was very
difficult to afford
to bring this language into any space, it
is still p it happened because I am the same
Nechuy-Levytskyi with his novel Clouds,
which is a very important author for the
same Pidmohylny.
at a time when
avant-gardes very often want to break
everything old for something new, for
Pidmogylyny the traditions that I
spoke about Harold Bloom and the Western
Canon
Harold Bloom are very important
attempts to
discuss with them to drop them or that there is a class
lecture by Olena Halaika about Pidmohylyny, a
link to which we will leave in the description of
this podcast, where Galeta says that
Pidmohylyny very directly appeals to the
canonical predecessor alive at the time,
this predecessor is an
insensitive leftist because Don't hear it, the grandfather is
conditional, and Pidmogilny appeals to the
already mentioned Mykhailo Kotsyubyns whom
his hero Stepan Radchenko remembers is a morgana veil
that he takes from his friend,
which he later turns to in order to
choose fragments and so on, but this
is not a bad memory at all, it is an unwillingness to
burn, destroy and give up the moon,
in general, it was very interesting for me to
reread the city, it was from point of view of
canonization because there were not so
many stages in the history of Ukrainian
literature When we had to
think about this canonization in principle
and not just try to collect
everything we have in a cup and one of these stages is
these twentieth and in fact Roman misto
when I think about town, I still want to
say a few words about the plot, it is important
for our listeners, just to remind
them of the plot, there is a young guy, Stepan
Radchenko,
he comes from the village, but as
Solomiya Pavlychko rightly tells us, this is not
just a Selyuk, not an Odessan, and this is a Selyuk with a
certain even nationalist
background because he managed to fight for everyone,
we understand that this is a person who
chose different flags for us clamored to be
in different camps and actually did not stick
to any of them, that is, wherever the wind blows,
he ended up there and he goes to the city. Why does
he go to the city, because he is the
most talented in his village, he
shows the most initiative,
organizational skills, and so on. He
has to study,
but he comes to the city and what he
sees, well, he sees more
alternatives, more opportunities,
he sees people who are dressed differently,
he sees that there are simply more professions, he was
able to fill his life more, and
this is where his great Odyssey begins, a
great journey, in fact, to himself
because Roman misto
tells us about a rather small part of
time from the life of a young guy
who is trying to find out who he is
in general. Against this background, he
meets different men who
occupy different positions in the life of this
city, and we meet, let's say, such
different role models, we also meet
several women and
very different romances take place with them within these Romances
Step himself An Radchenko is also very different and, in
parallel, Stepan Radchenko is finally trying to
become a writer
about this novel. It is important for me to
say what I mean about the plot. What is
actually the evidence that
Pidmohylnyi conceived it as a
screenplay for a movie and that is why
there is such a fast plot. There is a very
many such sharp theatrical
turns because it adds suspense to the
film, in the end we still
have a novel and it is probably a sin to regret it
because it is not known what the fate of the film would be,
instead this novel became
truly key for the history of Ukrainian
literature and returning to the topic of the city
what there is a city in this novel, I tend
to think that the city is just one of the
possible backgrounds, at the same time the city is a sieve
that passes the main character through it
and tries to
offer him to
maneuver himself or surrender to the
elements, and here each of us at different
stages of our lives can consider
whether is he more of a fatalist or does he believe in
his own will I think Stepan Radchenko k
if you ask him, he
probably wouldn't say himself, is he a fatalist or does
he believe in his will, because on the one
hand he is so self-confident and so
on, on the other hand, we constantly see how
he is affected by the choices of others and the decisions of
others and how
his mood simply changes dramatically in fact, Stepan Radchenko is
somewhat exaggerated in some ways. But perhaps
we can also find the answer in Pidmogilny himself,
who says that he
conceived this whole story as a comedy
. In fact, the fact that the city is not an
obsessive character of this work for me is important to me.
That is, it is not primarily a novel
about the city The novel is communist Yes, but
it is not intended to describe the Kyiv of that
time, it is intended to explore the
modern Undertaker hero of that time,
who may not have clear views, who is
looking for himself, who wants happiness, wants joy,
and it is simply good literature But at the
expense of the fact that it is good literature we
get these additional benefits as it
always happens with cool works of
art. That is, we get a large
city th Novel Actually, I wanted to talk to you
about these characters like
Stepan Radchenko, who are not quite
good guys, but at the same time, you would
n't call them bad guys, and what
they are like from the point of view of literature, because I
will share with you that when I reread the
city this time in my there were very fresh
memories of re-reading the notes of the
snub-nosed Mephistopheles Vinnychenko and There the
main character is older, he
has much more money, but he is also
a bit like
where the wind blows him there and carries him despite the
fact that, again, he is a lawyer, that is, he is a
lawyer, and he has to set it up pawns and
knocking them down on the horrors, when you
look at Stepan Radchenko today, he
does not resonate with you, so tell me about this emotion.
Why does this character not resonate with you, if
he is beating you, what did he annoy you,
no, he is
not close to me at this particular moment of my
life and I accept it for myself, it does not
mean that I
must necessarily associate myself with each character No, I
can be an observer from the side I
just have for myself the opportunity to
escape into this text and be there next to
him, let him annoy me with all
his lovers.
one and a half years, in fact, the time
during which the events of the work take place
change so drastically and so to speak,
that everything is changed, so we understand that
this novel
offers us a hero that the author
constructed, he invented this
hero for himself, this hero of an
intellectual, because both reading and
literature, which Stepan Radchenko is fond of,
are actually that what
Valerian Podmohylyny is interested in and what he is interested in.
And that is why we can understand
that this text is autobiographical and talk
in this vein about the autobiography of this
text.
It is also
important for me that it is already the middle of the novel.
And this is normal promise when Stepan
Radchenko decided that the
page of his life begins with you, he needs to
start keeping a diary, note everything down,
and As soon as he began to start this diary,
it turned out that today is a
special anniversary, exactly one year ago, I
came to this city. You need to remember this date
and to celebrate her and to find
this celebration Stepan Radchenko
forgot that he needed to start
keeping a diary and decided to go out for a
walk in the city the
street received him quietly before the
evening rustle and his legs
measured her infused elastic strength tongues
worked on new steel springs the
boy walked leisurely defiantly
raising his head as a sign of supremacy, some
consciousness clearly took root in his head,
giving sparkling eyes and
calm prudence of movement to the very
process of this proud gait, the feeling of the
flawless work of each wheel of
his complex machine gave him such
intoxicating pleasure that he did not
even think about where exactly his feet were leading after getting
off on Khreshchatyk bought a newspaper for everyone
at a table in an open cafe and asked for
a coffee with a cake with an inexplicable and
unexpected delicacy, putting one
foot on the other, he lazily stirred a fragrant drink from a
spit, looking at the hundreds of faces that
floated past the bars, taking
in all the colorfulness and
acceleration of street traffic then he unfolded the
newspaper in the classifieds section and threw another cake
to the maid. The passing
symphony orchestra concert in the opera house
convinced him the most because he
had never heard of such concerts, and after getting on the
bus, even though it was only two blocks to go,
he reached Volodymyrska
Street, buying an
expensive ticket at the ticket office the guy began to
walk like a circling foil of Tisha, someone's spectacle of
incessantly changing faces, put on clothes
, the crowd had a strange effect on him. He
continued to watch this crowd, he went to
this concert and did not listen very carefully to him,
but during the intermission he realized that
undoubtedly everyone around were cultured
people who read magazines and a lot which of
them is for we would have the honor to meet a
talented writer, but in the meantime, they are
shared by a very sick person, making
him a foreign body that accidentally
got inside a well-functioning
organism.
material existence, he was lonely, and the
months of human exploits were now
turning into his shame,
at the end of this episode, he will
meet his third love, the
Zoska kiyanka. And actually from this
fragment, I understand for myself that this is a Kyiv text,
in particular, despite what you said a few
minutes ago that he does not necessarily have to
be from Kyiv, but here it is. The city of
Pidmogilny belonged to several cities
at the same time. He was from the Dnipro and about the Dnipro. A
small drama about his texts. He was a
Kharkiv author. He was from Kyiv.
He belonged to the Kyiv organization of the branch,
and this text has so many
markings streets,
alleys, places, what can we say
such a pattern of reproaches istati
We are walking through the city of Pidmogilny and this
will really be a template that we will
work on because there are so many
places that Stepan Radchenko used
to go and today we walk in these places and this is
actually the Kyiv text and this is the
belonging of the marking of specific
streets of specific moods of a specific
environment that, for example, came to the theater
and to which he does not quite belong, they
also read magazines, they are interested in
art, but they are different from him, and he has
not done anything during this year, during his stay
in this place, to get closer to them.
Do you agree with Bohdana
that this is a text about Kyiv, a novel about Kyiv if
I didn't agree, I'd be an idiot. Of course
I agree, and what's more, I would very much like
our Kyiv space to be marked with a
gravestone and signs from the Graveyard,
or for example, I sometimes go to a
coffee shop in Na Valakh precisely because it is
approximately where I had I wish I could live with my
second love, the hero of Undertaker, and
that I wouldn't be there. It's nice to think about it,
I'm clinging to something you know, that is, when
we talk about this theater audience, we
also understand that if the reader were to read this to
Paris, where Pidmohylnyi also visited, or to
any other city, he would be able to
understand this. That is, we, through Stepan
Radchenko, have the opportunity to look at the city with the eyes of a
neophyte.
social institutions, how does the theater work,
how does the institute work, how does the
street work, how does the expensive clothing store work,
we look at some such, how would it be better to
say, both at the top and at the bottom,
and together with Radchenko we try on some
emotions for ourselves because you know, I really
like this the fragment that you
read is also like this, even this is even
neuroticism, it is somehow already sarcasm in
Pidmogilny, because Radchenko, who has been
living in Kyiv for a year, and in fact, he has a
small but certain success, he begins to
flirt, that is, he is like that, saying Oh no, I am
so separate and all that And we understand
that this is a human trait, this is a certain
ability to exaggerate. This is the desire
to drive oneself into a certain critical
state. that this critical state then
provokes a certain creativity, we see that
Stepan Radchenko is nevertheless an artist, although
he is supposedly preparing himself for something else, because
in the school where he was supposed to study, he
was supposed to be preparing himself to
return to his native village and improve
his life and to make their collective
farms the best collective farms in the entire Soviet
Union and this foray into the city is temporarily
limited. And it is very practically
utilitarian, that is, to go study and
return himself. Pidmogilny, who
never obtained a certain higher education, was
also preparing himself for another. He was supposed to become a
polytechnic. Instead, he is studying French on his own
language to a level that
allows him to read and translate, he
begins to write very early. He
is also such a special type. But we
can all recognize among Ukrainian
contemporary artists similar people who supposedly
come from the outside, but it is this arrival
from the outside that gives them a rather unique
outsider's optics or despite the ironic Stepan
Radchenko towards the end - It's just a
mockery of him you, that is, when he
starts this tour of his loved ones. It
seems to me that he is already simply
carrying the Undertaker, he cannot help himself. It is very
funny to him because Stepan Radchenko
convinces himself at first, he so involuntarily
says oh, we have to find him there, see,
then he starts looking for her, although
he has just hesitated Does he need this, he is
already locked in here, he is already looking for her and he is like
Oh God, she will meet me How will it be?
Then he meets this woman and
it turns out that she is not his, she
was not waiting for him and so on. Well, what about Stepana
Radchenko? so youthful and how it
hurts him, this incredible amplitude of
emotions is very cool She manages to be a
gravedigger and Well, listen to her, we also
see what is given on our streets and not
only in people of Stepan Radchenko's age.
I can't find myself or find myself because it's
also interesting for me to think about
it here. Well, in the case of Radchenko, it's
finding yourself, it's returning to yourself,
it's discovering yourself that is, I don't fully
understand his
expedition, what he wants, but he
himself doesn't know that either, which is normal, and it's
some kind of
constant process of self-education and
trying to somehow hone and
shape yourself, because many people do it at the
university
. and
about this difference of the city that arises in
different societies, because for the
neoclassicists who have an impeccable
education, the city is a space where they
grow and where they find themselves
through the intellect, often through history, and for
Pidmogilny, the City, whether it is Dnipro,
Katerynoslav, or Kyiv, or anywhere what a different
city it will be in a space that he
comes from a different space and this does not
make his experience worse or better he is
simply different He allows us to get a
more complete picture of the city
than
if we looked at it only through the
gaze of the one and only Mykola Zarov,
you know, I also think about the fact that Solomiya
Pavlychko compares
Domontovych and Pidmohylny and she
explains why she does this despite
very, very different experiences. Both
Domontovych and Pidmohylnyi give this fuller
picture of the new city. Here it is important to say
that they are not describing it for the first time, but they
are describing it in this period.
and I really like this
juxtaposition because it shows us,
again, an incredibly ambitious beginning,
which was not just an
essay by some essay. And these are full-blooded
cool novels that tell us a lot
[music]
I think of Pidmohylyny as such,
you know in the good sense of the word amateur in
many things, he was not afraid to be
an amateur in order to become a
professional and he showed many a
rather unexpected path to
professionalism, which lies through a certain
sensuality, through a passionate interest, this
path is not through the university, and we understand
that these approaches can be combined, they
can exist separately and
work together but it is the Helper who
gives this cool model is possible for the first time and
shows that it can work
very powerfully, that is, you don't have
to
go all the way from the very beginning, it's supposed
to be right, so you can at some point
start to discover something for yourself and everything will
still be very cool. What do I think about
this Stepan radchenko and his constant
desire to find the
private key to this success, as he
supposedly sees it, and the desire to solve, here he
first wants to solve when he
arrives at his higher educational institution
where he has to make a number of different movements,
he does not want to do it, he is cool,
then he opens a
literary life for himself and also thinks that the
only way is to find these ways there, that's
why shake hands with him, drink
there, then go for a beer and the same story
wherever he ends up, it's actually and
betrays in him, in my opinion, a
person who gets into a new environment and is
not ready to penetrate it and act according to
its rules. And is simply looking for a
way to get a position in this
environment, which would be, well, this is me I'm not saying it
's very frequent, but the detours are so
quick and easy, that is, you don't understand the
city, but just come and get the cool
chair you're sitting on, God, you
answered why this novel does
n't fully
resonate with
me right now, because I'm not interested in the hero of Stepan Radchenko,
not the heroes of Pidmogylny I am more interested in
the heroes of Vedemontovych at this moment, who are
extraordinary people with a rich
inner world, of course with development and
search, but intellectuals a priori without
options and an insect and a teacher from a girl
with a bear, they
are already on, they are already representatives of the
scientific community And they are
much more interesting to me in fact, I also read a
novel about a city about a city before going to bed
every day for a month and a half, and I forgot to
tell you about it, but the
opportunity has come. I am reading it from the magazine Universe for
2012. It is a novel, and the local Albanian of the city is
not from Rome, such a composition, so
multifaceted, you can read it
differently, because here there is the Traveler Marco
Polo and there is a King, and this king asks that the
Traveler og lazy all the cities of his
kingdom and I will tell him about each of
them and this Marco Polo he classifies
cities I city memory city desire
city feeling city i.e. there are different
categories of these cities and among them there is even the
city of Anastasia which I was very
pleased It is nice and this the text can be read in
several ways, you can read by these
categories of cities about the city and the sky, all 5
or 6 texts about the city and eyes, all the
texts can be read in a row, there is also this game in
this game, I like that I can write about each
city these few paragraphs I can
grab them I can settle there I can
be with these living elements for a very
short period of time and then close and
stay in my space in my
country estate far from these not
always real cities
And that is why this intellectual journey
may be fictional but
not deliberately simplified
I like it. But while I was saying this, I
understood why I
especially like the city now,
because this is not the kind of novel that is written in
response to a complex, say in Well, let's
finally make a cool novel about the city of
Kyiv, in fact, the Undertaker is very
witty, ironic, sometimes
very cruel.
to
arrange his life in general, in a moment he
comes to the idea that it is not so bad to
be an alphonse, and at the same time he thinks about
how lucky women are, they say, a woman has
a husband, that's his problem, so that
she has everything OK, she ate normally and
somehow her basic needs were met
And when you read this sometimes
even despicable but very funny Undertaker,
you understand that the name is a city.
Well, it's apt, it's cool. And
when I look at the cover of the book
association's edition, I realize that it's so
laconic, I want to pick it up, but it's
also ironic because that the novel that
tells us so much about Kyiv and gives us
information about this Kyiv actually
solves such problems what are called
eternal problems, eternal questions,
that is, the ability of a person to determine what
he wants and what he does not want, how he
wants, who he loves, what he is
interested in, who he sees himself in this
world, and just the background of the city here really becomes
non-trivial new, but I thought By the
way, today we will also talk about
Ukrainization, because Stepan Radchenko is
working on courses on Ukrainization. But
it is clear that for me it is not at all like
Germany.
But
this is, let's say, a fruit for
literary critics and for readers who
read on Skyphone, and not necessarily a
context in which to dive, because
there is necessarily a
context of this private journey of the
individual in depth and in general the
possibility or impossibility of making
such a journey and does the city help in
which there are far more irritants
than in the village and it would seem that she has you
over to go motivate to reveal yourself or
vice versa it prevents you And maybe you
could do it somewhere else, for example at
home and this is a terribly valuable city
because it is not intrusive it is not
intrusive ideologically it does not solve
these great eternal problems of Ukrainian
literature it does not is going to perform
some super function. That is, it's just a
cool novel and this is probably its
special novelty
[music]
friends. Today we talked about Valeryan's novel The
Cemetery City, but
at the end I want to set up such a bulletin
board and remind about certain
things, first of all, Bohdana and I will leave several
materials in the description for this episode,
in particular, the lecture by Olena Galeta, which
Bohdana mentioned, the lecture by Yaryna
Tsymbal, which I want to mention, as well as the release
of a podcast called the morning
dose, which was once published by the collaboration of
Ukrainian Pravda and the Ukrainian
Institute of Books, where there is a fragment of the beginning of the
novel, the city if you it has not yet been
reread or read suddenly never
You can obey here is this fragment, these 35
minutes of introduction, in order to immerse yourself in
this text and further discover it for yourself
, it can also be very good
and an adventure for you. So
we will leave all these links in the description of our episode,
it is on the apple prompt, Google podcast in
YouTube Well, she can also listen to
us on Spotify, rate us,
please leave comments on almost
all comments on YouTube. I even try to
answer so that you feel
this contact. If you want to ask something,
don't be afraid to write to us in
private messages, because we are very happy to
go. on contact and we are very interested to
discuss with you, communicate,
agree or, on the contrary, find
counterarguments, which can also be
friends if you are abroad. And we know that
we are listened to a lot outside of Ukraine,
please share.
in what other countries do these imaginary
audio living rooms appear in which you and I
meet, we find it extremely interesting
Yes I do I want to add
What is very important to me is that
literature always works in
relationships, and we started with these
relationships using the example of the grave. It is
very cool to
test them and
try to understand how they work. The
novel, the city, despite the fact that it is just a
good and very fast text, you must
read With the thought that the
plot was not the most important thing for Pidmohylyny,
he constantly declares it and that is probably
why he has very clean and interesting
plots that you want to follow and this is a good
opportunity to think about the Ukrainian
literary canon and how
generations interact and that how do
literatures interact with each other,
friendship, we were very happy
to hear from you, but also We really want to hear from you
in Ivano-Frankivsk, but someone who will
listen to this podcast later will not
understand what I am talking about And we
will have an edition in Ivano-Frankivsk already this week on Thursday
which we record live and it will be
dedicated to
one big conversation about one language, you and
I know very well that the language is
Ukrainian, there is something to talk about you I really
want to meet and see our
Ivano-Frankivsk audience if you
suddenly join us there on the
industrial device And in the description there will be a link to all
all the details to the new meetings everything by
all bye See you soon
[music]